Inter-Institutional Study Committee records, 1941-1961 C301
Indiana University Archives
Inter-Institutional Study Committee records
1941-1961
1949-1952
Indiana University Archives
Inter-Institutional Study Committee (Ind.)
C301
1.2 cubic feet
In July of 1949, the Inter-Institutional Study Committee, also known as the Four State Schools Committee, was created in response to a new law passed by the Indiana Legislation requesting that the four state schools submit a formula by which the state funds would be divided amongst the institutions. The committee was comprised of representatives from Indiana University, Purdue University, Ball State Teachers College, and Indiana State Teachers College. The collection consists of correspondence, minutes, preliminary studies, raw data, and five bound reports.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Administrative History
In the summer of 1949, the presidents and comptrollers of Indiana University, Purdue University, Indiana State Teachers College, and Ball State Teachers College got together to discuss the formation of a committee to solve a problem posed by the Indiana State Legislation. In the previous months a law had been passed concerning the state budget and its distribution among the state schools. The law stated:
1. Cost per student both on-campus and off-campus
2. Number of students, including the number of students in each department
3. Number of out-of-state students
4. Housing costs, etc
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Administrative files; Four State Schools Study Data; Four State Schools Physical Plant Study; and Bound reports.
Scope and Content Note
The Inter-Institutional Study Committee's records range from 1941-1961 with the bulk of the material being dated 1949-1952. It is arranged into four series: Administrative files; Four State Schools Study Data; Four State Schools Physical Plant Study; and Bound reports.
The first series is Administrative files. It consists of correspondence, minutes, reports, and a few records of a sub-committee created to study the capitol needs of the institutions. The bulk of the correspondence is either to or from Joseph A. Franklin, but it also includes a number of letters between President Herman B Wells of Indiana University and President Frederick L. Hovde of Purdue University. The reports provide details about the individual goals of the committee and document the final budget formula. It spans the years 1941-1961.
The second series, Four State Schools Study Data, ranges from 1949-1953. This series contains budgetary information, studies done by the committee, forms, and miscellaneous material from three of the institutions. The bulk of the data pertains to Indiana University and Purdue University.
The Four State Schools Physical Plant Study is the next series. It is mostly comprised of the forms that the committee used in this study but also includes instructions to the institutions on how to fill out these forms correctly. The forms have been placed into separate files except for forms 4 and 6. These are kept together since they appeared that way in the original collection and seem to compliment each other. The collection originally contained ten or so blank copies of each form, but all but one of these copies were discarded. Materials in this series are mostly undated. Those dated range from 1951-1952.
The last series is Bound reports. It consists of five bound reports made by the committee in 1952, as well as a letter from Briscoe to Franklin. The letter is accompanied by a report which, consequently, seems to be a later draft of the preliminary report made by the committee. These bound reports are summaries of the committee's achievement. The reports cover each institution separately and then together showing the school's budgets for 1952 collectively and by department.
Related Material
See also the Inter-Institutional Study Committee series in the Dean of Faculties records, Collection 26.
See also Accession 2000/062, consisting of the Bureau of Facilities Programming and Utilization's records on the Inter-Institutional Study Committee, 1961-1967.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0464
Appraisal
Duplicates discarded.
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Finance --Law and legislation.; Government aid to higher education --Indiana.; Ball State Teachers College -- Finance; Indiana State Teachers College -- Finance; Inter-Institutional Study Committee (Ind.) -- Archives; Inter-Institutional Study Committee (Ind.) -- Records and correspondence; Inter-Institutional Study Committee (Ind.) -- History -- Sources; Indiana University -- Finance; Purdue University -- Finance
- Administrative files, 1941-1961
  - Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Reports, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Four State Schools Study Preliminary Brochure, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Four State Schools Building Study Committee, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
- Four State Schools Study Data, 1949-1953
  - Indiana University and Purdue Budgets, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Study of Credit Hour Comparison, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Space Needs (by institution and department), undated (Box 1)
  - Forms and Data on Expenses other than Overhead, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Indiana University Statistics, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Purdue University Statistics, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Advanced Registration Process, Ball State Teachers College, undated (Box 1)
- Four State Schools Physical Plant Study, 1951-1952
  - Instructions for Forms, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Physical Plant Study worksheets (Box 2)
    - Sheet 1, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheet 2, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheet 3, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheets 4 & 6, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheet 5, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheet 7, undated (Box 2)
    - Sheet 8, undated (Box 2)
- Bound reports, 1952
  - Pilot Study, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University Inter-Institutional Study Committee Summary, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Purdue University Inter-Institutional Study Committee Summary, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Ball State Teachers College Inter-Institutional Study Committee Summary, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Indiana State Teachers College Inter-Institutional Study Committee Summary, 1952 (Box 2)